to its natural end. So by having death as a part of the cultural and social fabric of life, people's everyday decisions about their health and healthcare are affected. The patriarch of my husband's maternal clan, Nenet Katcha, is now approaching the age of 100, as far as we can tell. And there are increasing signs that he is about to depart on his own journey for Puya. And his death will be greatly mourned. But I know that my husband's family looks forward to the moment when they can ritually display what his remarkable presence has meant to their lives, when they can ritually recount his life's narrative, weaving his story into the history of their community. His story is their story. His funeral songs will sing them a song about themselves. And it's a story that has no discernible beginning, no foreseeable end. It's a story that goes on long after his body no longer does. People ask me if I'm frightened or repulsed by participating in a culture where the physical manifestations of death greet us at every turn. But I see something profoundly transformative in experiencing death as a social process and not just a biological one. In reality, the relationship between the living and the dead has its own drama in the U.S. healthcare system, where decisions about how long to stretch the thread of life are made based on our emotional and social ties with the people around us, not just on medicine's ability to prolong life. We, like the Torajans, base our decisions about life on the meanings and the definitions that we ascribe to death. So I'm not suggesting that anyone in this audience should run out and adopt the traditions of the Torajans. It might be a little bit difficult to put into play in the United States. But I want to ask what we can gain from seeing physical death not only as a biological process
hasta su fin natural. Así que al considerar la muerte como parte del tejido cultural y social de la vida, las decisiones diarias de la gente sobre su salud y su cuidado se ven afectadas. El patriarca del clan maternal de mi esposo, Nenet Katcha, está llegando a los 100 años de edad, por lo que podemos sabemos. Y hay signos crecientes de que está próximo a partir hacia su propio viaje a Puya. Y su muerte se lamentará enormemente, pero sé que la familia de mi esposo espera con ilusión el momento en el que puedan manifestar de forma ritual lo que su notable presencia ha significado en sus vidas, y puedan contar ritualmente la narración de su vida, tejiendo su historia en la historia de su comunidad. La historia de él es la historia de ellos. Sus cantos fúnebres les cantarán una canción sobre ellos mismos. Y es una historia que no tiene un inicio discernible, ni un final previsible. Es una historia que continúa hasta mucho después de que el cuerpo ya no continúe. La gente me pregunta si siento temor o repulsión por participar en una cultura donde las manifestaciones físicas de la muerte nos saludan a cada paso. Pero veo algo profundamente transformador en experimentar la muerte como un proceso social y no sólo como uno biológico. En realidad, la relación entre la vida y la muerte tiene su propio drama en el sistema de salud de Estados Unidos, donde las decisiones sobre cuánto estirar el hilo de la vida están basadas en nuestros vínculos emocionales y sociales con la gente que nos rodea, no sólo en la habilidad de la medicina en prolongar la vida. Nosotros, como los torajanos, basamos nuestras decisiones sobre la vida en los significados y definiciones que le atribuimos a la muerte. No estoy sugiriendo que todos en la audiencia deban correr y adoptar las tradiciones de los torajanos. Podría ser un poco difícil hacerlo en los Estados Unidos. Pero quiero plantear qué podemos ganar al ver la muerte física no sólo como un proceso biológico
but as part of the greater human story. What would it be like to look on the expired human form with love because it's so intimately a part of who we all are? If we could expand our definition of death to encompass life, we could experience death as part of life and perhaps face death with something other than fear. Perhaps one of the answers to the challenges that are facing the U.S. healthcare system, particularly in the end-of-life care, is as simple as a shift in perspective, and the shift in perspective in this case would be to look at the social life of every death. It might help us recognize that the way we limit our conversation about death to something that's medical or biological is reflective of a larger culture that we all share of avoiding death, being afraid of talking about it. If we could entertain and value other kinds of knowledge about life, including other definitions of death, it has the potential to change the discussions that we have about the end of life. It could change the way that we die, but more importantly, it could transform the way that we live. (Applause)
sino como parte de la gran historia humana. ¿Cómo sería mirar a la forma humana fallecida con amor porque es una parte íntima de lo que todos somos? Si pudiésemos expandir nuestra definición de la muerte para abarcar la vida, podríamos experimentar la muerte como una parte de la vida y quizás enfrentar a la muerte con algo distinto al miedo. Quizás una de las respuestas a los desafíos que enfrentamos en el sistema de salud de Estados Unidos, especialmente con respecto a los cuidados del fin de la vida, sea tan simple como un cambio de perspectiva, y el cambio de perspectiva en este caso sería mirar la vida social de cada muerte. Nos ayudaría a reconocer que la forma en que limitamos nuestras conversaciones sobre la muerte como algo que es médico o biológico es una reflejo de una cultura más amplia que todos compartimos, la de evadir la muerte, teniendo miedo de hablar sobre ella. Si pudiésemos considerar y valorar otras clases de conocimiento sobre la vida, incluyendo otras definiciones de la muerte, tendríamos el potencial de cambiar las discusiones que tenemos sobre el fin de la vida. Podría cambiar la forma en que morimos, pero más importante, podría transformar la forma en que vivimos. (Aplausos)